yeah so hi I'm George I'm the founder of
stackpack but I'll tell you about that
at the moment but this is about making
coding assistants smarter for dsls not
DSL specifically but like for things
that require like the worst part of
coding that LMS are terrible at so tell
you about
that whoa
okay tell you a bit about me first so
I'm the founder of stackpack stackpack
makes the worst part of coding that LM
suat which is infrastructure and devops
work configuring all the different
devops tools together uh much easier so
developers can have more fun Building
Products before that I was a founding
engineer at a couple of startups I love
doing calisthenics which is like body
weight exercises riding motorcycles and
volunteering Tech Community running free
boot camps and stuff like that I'm
really into developer experience and
security which are two things that
usually don't mix really well
um yeah and today I'm going to talk
about dsls not specifically dsls because
if you have a ml file or Json that
follows a specific schema it's not a DSL
it's a generic like configuration
language but LM still suck at it they're
pretty terrible and to give you an idea
what dsls are and why they're important
we use them in every single project like
SQL is a DSL uh tform code Docker
compose graph kubernetes manifest Rego
anyone written Rego before for opa
yeah most people don't so yeah so we use
all these kind of different dsls in our
projects in different ways and LMS are
pretty terrible at them for the
following reasons we're going to explain
why but we need them um in our coding
and llms are really good at the good
part of coding which is writing the
actual code but they're pretty terrible
of the part we don't enjoy which is
figuring out all these different dsls or
domain specific languages so why llm
suck at dsls so this this is a paper
about domain specific languages with two
different evaluation methods I will
describe now um trying to explain why
them ssls so you would see on the left
column there's a stack eval so these are
a set of questions from stack Overflow
about different dsls and answers and
here they're evaluating different models
on these dsls and on the other side
you'd see stack unseen which are very
recent more fresh stack overlow
questions that most likely the model was
not trained on and You' see like the
performance Falls rapidly with the
Unseen data so one of the main issues
with dsls
is they keep changing quickly and not
all of the dsls have a lot of data
compared to JavaScript in Python um as
you can see on the graph on the right
side so the performance drops greatly
the more less the less popular the
language is and the less data that went
into training the llm so there are two
things here at Play so how much data was
in the training data set of the llm from
these dsls different dsls or less
popular languages and at the same time
how fresh this data was because when you
see the freshness of the data set or the
questions drops for the most recent
questions uh performance drops as well
for domain specific languages and the
less popular the languages performance
also drops as well so the main issue
with dsls they're very fragmented there
are a lot of them so there are not a lot
of data in the data set about these dsls
and the more the DSL or the schema
changes frequently the worse the llm
would do so to give you an idea of this
for
example um if you compare
JavaScript to kubernetes manifests as if
you consider this like specific schema
of configuring kubernetes DSL kubernetes
gets a new major release a new minor
release every three months so it keeps
changing so most ofms don't know what
the latest version is so definitely to
perform worse according to this study
and kubernetes is just very recent
compared to python for example like how
often does the python syntax change
compared to kubernetes manifest schema
or like configuration parameters so yeah
that's basically why LMS suck at dsls so
much this is something we're in
internally trying to compare
different uh open source and closed
Source uh LM models I'm not sure like
the text is pretty small but like here
you would find metal Lama Mistral gbd 40
and Claude 3.5 on it on different
applications so this was we were
generating terraform code for different
Cloud providers and we found out that
there's another Factor so the freshness
is a factor the popular popularity of
the language is a factor and the third
one is the task itself so you would see
Lama sucks pretty much configuring Azure
it's pretty terrible at it compared to
other models and they perform
differently for different Cloud
providers so the task also um impacts
how these llms perform on different DLS
so today I'm going to talk to you about
four techniques some of the stuff we
tried these ones fist together like you
can see they Burger um so you it would
help you remember them but there are
other things we keep trying all the time
to make LMS better at these kind of dsls
and like configuration languages um but
the four we're going to talk about are
bounded decoding retriev magic
generation grammar prompting and
Recovery there are more obvious things
related to prompting techniques uh but
these are the ones that like had the
biggest impact
so the first one is boundary decoding so
first let me know like who's building an
ad powered app
here who's building llm
agents Okay cool so bound and decoding
or structure generation this is how to
do proper structure generation so to
give you an idea of how it works we take
an example so this reg X can someone
tell me what this regx
does in the middle on the middle so this
is a reg
for creating a a number with a decimal
point so the first part is you have one
or more digits and then an optional
decimal point and then zero or more
digits afterwards
okay
yeah yeah I didn't escape the dot so
this hopefully generates um and actually
like there's also another mistake like
the D behind like the digit behind the
dot like if you have a DOT you should
have a digit like you shouldn't have a
dot so assuming this is a valid reg X to
generate numbers with decimal points so
how do we force the llm to generate
valid numbers every single point of time
like 100% of the time so this is what
bounding decoding does so how llms work
like I'm butchering this but like the
last layer you you get like the
probability of different tokens so if
you have these input sequence 74 eight
you get from the llm the probabilities
of the next tokens so for the plus you
get 3% probability F you get 4% assume
this is a token and then dot 7% and so
on so what's structured decoding is we
take a regx and then we build a finite
automaton based on this regx so we start
and then we have a digit between 0 and 9
and then we have another digit because
this is at least one digit and then we
can keep going generating more more
digits and at some point we can end it's
an integer there's no decimal point or
we can add a point and then add more
more digits as many as we want and then
end so do you understand this tomaton
how it works yeah it's very simple right
okay so we use this and walk step by
step taking in the input and we zero out
we mask the probabilities of all the
tokens that are not valid as transitions
so in this case we have we're in this
state and the valid tokens are either
another digit or a decimal
point so anything else we just mask out
we zero the probability
and then we continue decoding as well so
we can only get the next token and we
would still be valid within this
automaton so the cool thing about finite
automaton is you can turn reg xes into
finite automatons you can turn a context
free grammar into finite automaton so
generic programming languages they're
not all context free but you can Define
in most of the cases a simpler version
of the grammar which is context free
which then you can turn into a finite
automaton and then you can control the
coding this way so
the cool thing about this is you
can take for example like what we did
like we created a context free grammar
for terraform and then we created a
finite automaton based on that and then
we get 100% of the time valid terraform
every single time so we forced the the
llm to generate valid DSL every single
point of time this is how to do proper
structure generation so some llm
providers like anthropic they don't do
that like they rely on the model being
very smart so they try prompt it into
generic Json but it screws up for two
for example but uh gbd4 and using this
Library like this explanation I brought
it in from the dotex outlines
documentation it's the best one out
there I found and if you use the
outlines library on top of an existing
open source llm it would be able to do
that like generate 100% valid output
every single
time so this is how it shows so I use
this test a lot to make sure structure
generation is proper so when you use
this technique to make sure you generate
bform code and you ask the LM who are so
the LM will output something like this
so this is basically for those who don't
know terraform um all resource that uses
a local exec provider to Echo out I am a
devops engineer so it forces the llm to
generate valid tform code even if you
ask it something outside like of the
bound tasks or like out of
domain and LMS are pretty clever in
finding workarounds that's why this
works so the second technique in Burger
is is retriever augmented generation
who's familiar with retriever augmented
generation okay so for those of you that
don't know retrieve augmented generation
you basically take in the user prompt
and context like selected bit of code um
or the user's environment like cursor
takes in the the the projects code or
like external documentation whatever and
then you retrieve more context and this
context may be anything like it can be
related code like the first version of
get up co- pilot and can be standard
operating procedures your own set of
best practices on how you want to
generate stuff it can also scour the web
like scrap web pages and it can be
documentation can be anything and then
you use the users context and this
external context to generate something
and this usually improves performance or
makes the llms more customizable so this
is the generic idea so what we learned
was that there are three things at least
you can do to make rag much better at
dsls and like very specific
configurations the first one is query
expansion so you don't just like take
the user query and then try to Reeve Mar
contest you can use an llm which can be
a small llm it doesn't have to be smart
to break down the query and rewrite
parts of it so one thing you can do is
extract keywords which we found is
amazing for dsls because in dsls you
have a lot of very specific technical
keywords and abbreviations and these
abbreviations make sense within the DSL
but they don't make sense to the llm
because this is a very minor part of the
data that was trained on the other part
we found that works really well is reite
the user query into a more expansive
query that may helps the llm understand
what the user is asking for and filters
and this works really well compared to
sematic search because most people doing
rag with sematic search when it comes to
domain specific languages and domain
specific problems it's super tough
because people create the dsls to be
more suent to be able to express stuff
to complicated configure complicated
Tools in a very easy suent way instead
of having to explain and elaborate but
the llms don't know that so you need to
expand and elaborate to make it easier
to match with relevant outside
context so I found keyword matching
better than semantic search when it
comes to retrieval with dsls the second
part is documentation so why get up
copilot and cursor suck so much at this
kind of infrastructure work is that they
reference mostly code samples not
documentation sources so we found if we
replace rag using Code samples with
documentation sources you get better
fresher results because for example for
terraform like how many companies open
source their Tero code on like the
public internet most people don't so
most of the terap code out there and the
docker files are outdated they're pretty
old so when you reference the latest
documentation you get higher quality
results although the example is not code
it's just
stocks the third thing we found out that
make rag much better and this is a
recurring theme we mix static analysis
with with generation so in this case we
use treer which is like a generic
parsing
uh like generic parser it pares most of
the popular languages and we par terap
from code kubernetes manifests Docker
files into code blocks and then we
figure out the relationships between
these code blocks and then we gener
summaries to index them so instead of
retrieving bits of text or blocks of
text from your configurations we
actually understand the structure of the
configurations and the relationships and
we use this to build more intelligent
trag and we use this to be able to
retrieve parts of your code and since we
know the relationships it's not just
semantic relationship it's actually
very deterministic graph of the
components building your infrastructure
or the relationships between the steps
of your C ICD for example and so
on the third technique of burger is
grammar prompting so you can find the
paper uh down there the grammar Port
prompting paper basically does is it
defines the grammar of the DSL or the
language you're trying to generate in
BNF
format and then adds a couple of
examples like if you prompting and then
prompts the llm so it basically tries to
teach the llm the rules of constructing
stuff or generating stuff in this
language so it generates more accurate
results so we tested this on internal
DSL generation benchmarks and increased
performance by 12% which is amazing but
we found this actually much more useful
for dsls that are brand new or not known
for example we were building an endpoint
to transpile your terraform code into an
architecture diagram using a diam with
code tool called um eraser DSL and and
razor are you familiar with the Razer
the diagramming
tool okay so I invented a new DSL to
draw architecture diagrams so no LM know
about this tool so what we did is we
created a simple grammar for this tool
plus their documentation and we grammar
prompted it and they just learned how to
generate code for this DSL so this works
great but the other techniques are
better at well-known dsls this is
perfect for newer dis L that the L knows
nothing
about so so using this technique with a
very old very small model we're able to
generate architecture diagrams using the
DSL razor DSL with like eight times less
the cost eight times faster and as you
can see like you can even see the the
the cost reduction so compared to 01
with this basic technique you're able to
generate stuff eight times faster and at
least 500 times cheaper than 01 with
just a simple model and it's the same
for all these techniques so we were able
to be clawed
um a DSL generation with a llama 3.1
model which is super old and super
small so we don't need smarter models we
just need more reliable systems built
around these models so the final one
which is pretty obvious recovery and
retry so what you do here you also need
static analysis because when you
generate code with the DSL you need to
make sure the DSL is working so you try
par it if it doesn't work then you take
the feedback from the parser and then
give it back to the LM to try it's
simple but it works and if you pause it
and it works fine it doesn't mean it's
done like you need to validate it if
it's aform resource for example you need
to validate the schema to make sure all
the attributes are there there's nothing
deprecated it's actually should work
with the latest schema because like for
example for terraform AWS you get a new
um provider version every three or four
days so it keeps changing really fast
and if you validate it you get some
validation output that's not valid you
give it back to the LM to fix it so it's
it's pretty simple this has got even
more interesting with agents so we've
been building agents architecture to try
and make this even better because we
figured out even if you create valid
configurations and you push it to
production it would just fail so we name
our agents after minions and we found
out like the most interesting
architecture in Norbit which is the
naked minion do you know
Norbert okay so why the naked minion
because this is a very stupid and simple
agent architecture it can do only two
things it can ask the user for input and
it can run a command on your machine
and even with this very simple agent
architecture it was able to fix issues
that we couldn't detect
deterministically using validation and
paring for example you can reach the
limit of the VPC number of vpcs you can
create on AWS you can forgot to install
some stuff or like configure credentials
in your machine and with this more
smarter kind of retry and Recovery
mechanisms you're able to fix more
issues yeah and that's basically it I
would have loved to talk more about
evaluation but that's also a bit like a
a big topic on its own so please reach
out and yeah thank
you any questions yeah
um no I haven't tried LM I'm I'm sure LM
can generate dsls but I haven't tried
but like even if the llm generate dsls
and then you're trying to make another
llm work with these dsls you would have
to use some of these techniques to make
it like be able to figure this out
because it's not like it's not
inherently like built inside its memory
or like
parameters yeah we'd have to learn it
this exactly the same way like all these
techniques we're trying to teach llms
how to understand the this and do better
so
yeah
yeah SS
it's a more generic
grammar it's it's manual like we tried
using for all of these things we use
llms to refine the prompts and optimize
these things but like in writing grammar
it's pretty terrible so grammar itself
is in a DSL and this is one of the very
few cases when if we try these
techniques to make it better at writing
grammar dsls it's not even better
because it's a lot like it's a it's more
complicated it requires a lot of
reasoning and to be able structure
grammar so this is basically a a very
slow manual process of iterating on the
grammar to make it generic enough so
Lama CPP for example would be able to
understand it and generate at the same
time it wouldn't time out because um it
can take you a lot like if you have a
lot of branching within the grammar for
example it can time out and just like
generate nothing so it's not the full
grammar for the thing you try generate
it's more of a like a bounded approach
and we found that llms are very
sensitive to the grammar so if you
switch around some rules it would be
like prompt engineering so you have to
mix the Grammar with prompting and the
llm is sensitive to the grammar so the
way you structure your grammar um would
like would generate different results so
the combination of rules and how we
break it it also matters for some reason
I'm not sure why but it
does
yeah yeah
tried
what have I tried
what we actually no but we're trying
that for agents so one of the things in
evaluation is that you need some sort of
high like there are three three levels
valuation for agents at least that's
what we we discovered you can evaluate
the end goal you can evaluate sub goals
and you can can evaluate the trajectory
of thinking like having a partial
partially ordered plan of some sort and
to have this partially ordered plan you
need a lot of examples on how to
accomplish the tasks like how the the
sequence of steps to to achieve the task
and we couldn't find a data set for
devops tasks so what we're doing is
we're creating very stupid agents like
Norbert that keeps like yeah basically
like a Terminator that tries to
accomplish the task and fails most of
the time and then let it run on
different scenarios and then filter
these scenarios with the ones that suc
Ed and then take these generate Center
operating procedures or like a word
model to guide the L the agent and then
try again and keep doing that until we
have like a a nice data
set that's as close as we got to
reinforcement
learning okay thank you